Guide to the Washington Office on Latin America Records, 1962-2020 and undated, bulk 1974-2005; 1962-ongoing RL.01401
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Initiatives and Activities Series, 1980-2008 and undated, 115 boxes
  - Advocacy Training Program, 1995-2003 and undated, 9.5 boxes
    Files for WOLA's Central America Advocacy Training Program (ATP). The ATP's primary objective is to build the capacity of local civil society organizations to advocate for rights protection in their respective societies. Divided into folder groups for Administrative Files and Project Files. The Administrative Files mostly concern the activities of WOLA's Washington D.C.-based staff and cover a range of administrative topics, including office correspondence; grants and funding documents; project planning and external reviews of projects; office memoranda; and some research files. The Project Files mostly reflect the work of WOLA staff working in Guatemala, Honduras, and Nicaragua. Material includes conference and workshop agendas; training and educational materials; and numerous project proposals for various Central American civil society organizations. Major topical groups include police reform, the administration of justice, and violence against women. Administrative files created by Central America-based offices may be found in the Administrative Files group.
    - Administrative Files, 1995-2003, undated (Box 294-300)
    - Project Files, 1997-2003, undated (Box 300-303)
  - Conferences and Programs, 1980-2006 and undated, bulk 1995-2005, 9 boxes
    Files documenting WOLA's involvement in various meetings on topics germane to its mission. Divided into folder groups for Events and Summits. Events consist of conferences and other programs such as brown bag lunches, speeches by visiting scholars and dignitaries, and seminars. Most of these were organized by WOLA staff, though conferences organized by the Latin American Studies Association (LASA) are also included. Most events involve human rights in some way, though they cover the scope of WOLA's activities. Summits contain files related to major international meetings. The largest group of files relate to the Summit of the Americas, held in Miami in 1994 and in Santiago, Chile in 1998. In addition, material on a 1996 sustainable development summit in Bolivia and the Civil Society for Hemispheric Integration Project (CSHIP) are also included.
    - Events, 1980-2006, undated (Box 303-308)
    - Summits, 1994-1998 (Box 308-311)
  - Drug Policy, 1987-2004 and undated, 23 boxes
    Files primarily relating to U.S. efforts to combat drug cultivation in the Americas and its sale in this country. Divided into the following four groups: Drugs, Democracy, and Human Rights Project; Research Files; U.S. Relations; and WOLA Files. Drugs, Democracy, and Human Rights Project (DDHR) files specifically pertain to the WOLA initiative of the same name, directed by Coletta Youngers and Eileen Rosin. The bulk of the material consists of drafts of papers and book chapters written for inclusion in Drugs and Democracy in Latin America: US Policy, an edited volume produced as part of the project. Research Files include notes, clippings, articles, and reports collected by WOLA staff for the DDHR Project and other activities. Topics covered in this group include aerial fumigation of coca crops, drug-related money laundering, and aerial interdiction of planes smuggling drugs out of South America. Most files specifically refer to Perú, though documents on Colombia and Bolivia are also well represented. This group also includes a small run of issues of Coca Bulletin, and English language newsletter promoting crop substitution printed in Bolivia. U.S. Relations files directly relate to the policies and actions of various offices of the federal government. The bulk of these are files on various Congressional hearings on pending U.S. legislation or oversight of Executive Branch activities such at those by the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) or the Executive Office of National Drug Control Policy (ONDCP). Other files concern the CIA (most relating to allegations of drug profiteering in connection with the Nicaragua-centered Contra War), FBI, and various branches of the U.S. military. Numerous documents declassified through Freedom of Information Act requests are included, most concerning the ONDCP. WOLA Files include administrative planning documents, internal correspondence and memoranda, articles by WOLA staff, and material related to conferences on drug policy coordinated and/or attended by WOLA. Documents created by WOLA staff, including Charles Call, Eileen Rosin, John Walsh, and Coletta Youngers. Researchers interested in drug policy should also consult Geographic subseries for Bolivia, Colombia, and Mexico. The Coletta Youngers Papers, also held by the Rubenstein Library at Duke, also contain pertinent files.
    - Drugs, Democracy, and Human Rights Project, 2001-2004, undated (Box 312-314)
    - Research Files, 1987-2004, undated (Box 314-322)
    - U.S. Relations, 1990-2003, undated (Box 322-329)
    - WOLA Files, 1991-2004, undated (Box 329-334)
  - Hurricane Mitch, 1998-2002 and undated, 7 boxes
    Files documenting the responses of WOLA, the larger NGO community, and state governments to the devastation left in the wake of Hurricane Mitch, a massive storm that hit Central America in 1998. Files concern the countries most directly hit by the storm, most prominently Nicaragua and Honduras but also El Salvador and Guatemala. Material in this subseries chronicle WOLA's efforts to advocate for additional aid from the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) and to persuade USAID and other government agencies to sign on to the principles outlined at a meeting of world governments and NGOs in Stockholm, Sweden. The Stockholm Principles proposed a comprehensive restructuring of hurricane-affected countries that included enlarging and consolidating democratic civil society, improving agricultural and environmental practices, and reducing foreign debt. Printed material and reports by WOLA partners in the region, such as Confederación De Pueblos Autóctonos De Honduras (CONPAH) and Coordinadora Civil para la Emergencia y la Reconstrucción (CCER) are also included. Additionally, some files on appropriations and responses from the U.S. Congress and Executive Branch and the United Nations can be found here. Major topics include sustainable land practices; the plight of indigenous Central Americans and those of African ancestry; international donor nations and debt service reduction; and efforts to reduce prodigious gap between the wealthiest and poorest in the region. Files were created by WOLA staff including Vicki Gass, Eric Olson, and Geoff Thale. Geographic subseries for affected countries, particularly Nicaragua, Honduras, and El Salvador contain some additional Hurricane Mitch-related files.
    - Hurricane Mitch files (Box 335-341)
  - Legislative Files, 1988-2004, bulk 1995-2001, 7.5 boxes
    Documents the Washington Office on Latin America's efforts to influence U.S. policy, particularly with respect to drugs and foreign military and development aid. Consists of correspondence, Congressional debates, newspaper editorials, and memoranda related to pending U.S. legislation. Contains many information packets for Congressional policy aids known internally as "Hill drops." In addition to correspondence to members of Congress, a few letters to Secretaries of State, President Clinton, and foreign heads of state are also included. Major topics include the process of certifying the cooperation of foreign countries in U.S. anti-narcotics programs, particularly with respect to Mexico and Colombia; military aid and training assistance; Hurricane Mitch; and numerous efforts to protect funding for the Interamerican Development Bank's (IDB) Fund for Special Operations (FSO), which provides financial assistance to the weakest Latin American economies. Additional files on WOLA's legislative work can be found in individual Geographic or Initiatives and Activities Subseries, generally in folder groups for U.S. Relations or WOLA Files. Assembled and maintained by WOLA staff, chiefly William Spencer.
    - 1988-1995 (Box 342)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 343)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 344)
    - 1997 (Box 345)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 346)
    - 1998-2000 (Box 347)
    - 2000-2002 (Box 348)
    - 2003-2004 (Box 349)
  - Media Work, 1987-2005 and undated, 4.5 boxes
    Consists chiefly of clippings falling into three categories: Editorials, Op-Eds, and Reprints. Editorials are generally written by major U.S. newspapers. Some packets sent to newspapers by WOLA accompany clippings. Op-Eds, generally written by WOLA-staff, also mostly appeared in major U.S. newspapers. Reprints come from a variety of domestic and Latin American publications. Some directly refer to WOLA activities or personnel. Topics cover the extent of WOLA's work, including most countries in the Geographic Series as well as initiatives on Drug Policy, Hurricane Mitch, and Rights and Development. Most files were organized alphabetically, though some additions are unarranged.
    - Editorials, 1995-1999 (Box 349)
    - Op-Eds, 1988-2001 (Box 349-350)
    - Reprints, 1987-2005, undated (Box 350-353)
  - Rights and Development, 1988-2008 and undated, 37 boxes
    Files on diverse issues of economic development. The majority of material concerns financial assistance to Latin American countries from international sources, particularly international financial institutions (IFIs). Several multilateral development banks (MDBs) figure prominently, including the Interamerican Development Bank (IDB, IADB, BID in Spanish); and the World Bank (WB), especially the activities of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD). Subseries is categorized into the following folder groups: Country Files; Indigenous Rights and Rural Development; Interamerican Development Bank; Labor; Multilateral Aid; Other Material; Printed Material; Trade; U.S. Foreign Aid; and World Bank. All groups are unarranged, except Country Files and Printed Material, which are organized alphabetically. Material created by WOLA staff, particularly Eric Olson.
    - Country Files, 1991-2001 and undated (Box 354-356)
      Primarily files of clippings for most of the countries and regions in which WOLA is active, except Panama, Uruguay, and Suriname. A list of these can be found in the Geographic Series. Topics vary but include international trade agreements, elections, and labor and workers' rights.
    - Indigenous Rights and Rural Development, 1991-2002, undated (Box 357-358)
      Includes material on efforts to preserve indigenous Latin American communities or the economic integration of rural areas. Most files directly concern the tensions between these competing goals. Topics include sustainable development and agriculture. The environmental and social consequences of the Hidrovia Project, a proposed system of waterways connecting interior areas South America near the intersection of the Paraguay-Paraná-Uruguay-La Plata river system are a major focus. While the bulk of the group consists of correspondence and research files, some printed material, including Indigenous Affairs and Abya Yala News are also included.
    - Interamerican Development Bank, 1995-2001, undated (Box 359-366)
      Files, correspondence, and reports relating to the Interamerican Development Bank (IDB, IADB) also known in Spanish as the Banco Interamericano de Desarrollo (BID). Many documents in this grouping were authored by IDB personnel, including a number of board meeting agendas and proceedings. Major topics include civil society participation in IDB decision-making, sustainable development, poverty reduction, and the Fund for Special Operations (FSO) through which the IDB makes loans to highly indebted poor countries (HIPCs). A few files are related to relief prompted by Hurricane Mitch, though the bulk of these may be found in the Hurricane Mitch Subseries.
    - Labor, 1991-2001, undated (Box 366-367)
      Chiefly material on labor rights issues. The bulk of the files concern Guatemala and the U.S./Guatemala Labor Education Project (GLEP). Several of these files address the proposed investigation by the U.S. Trade Representative (USTR) of Guatemala's eligibility for the Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) given alleged abuses of labor activists. Additional files on the status of labor rights in Chile related to a proposed bilateral free trade agreement with the United States are also included.
    - Multilateral Aid, 1992-2000, undated (Box 368-369)
      Consists of general files on IFIs and MDBs, particularly relating to debt relief of HIPCs, as well as those involving collaborations between the IDB or WB and other institutions. Additional files on the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) are also included.
    - Other Material, 1992-2001, undated (Box 369-373)
      Files not fitting within other categories. Most involve general issues of economic development or human rights. These include files of economic indicators for countries, debt relief files not explicitly addressing the role of IFIs, private sector investment, and civil society development. Also includes files for specific WOLA personnel, including John Burstein, Bonnie Tenneriello, and Alex Wilde.
    - Printed Material, 1988-2008 and undated
      - Andean Development Corporation [ADC], 2000 Sept., 2 folders (Box 373)
      - AEC [Asociación de Economistas del Caribe], Cuadernos de la Coyuntura Caribeña, 1993 (Box 373)
      - [BIC] Bank Information Center, Citizen's Guide to World Bank Environmental Assessment Procedures, 1992 (Box 373)
      - Bonn International Center for Conversion, Defense Resources to Human Development, 1998 (Box 373)
      - CENCOS [Centro Nacional de Comunicacion Social], 1994 (Box 373)
      - CEPAL Notes [Comisión Economica para America Latina y el Caribe], 1992 Nov.-2001 Jan., 2 folders (Box 373)
      - CSIS [Center for Strategic and International Studies] election reports, 1998, 2000, 2 folders (Box 373)
      - Comisión Colombiana de Juristas, 1995, 1999 (Box 373)
      - CNDDHH [Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos], analysis of Peruvian torture problems, 1999 (Box 373)
      - Cuban American National Foundation, 1993 (Box 373)
      - Cuestión de Estado, 1993-1995 (Box 374)
      - Democracy: The Solution to the Haitian Crisis conference report, 1994 (Box 374)
      - The Development Gap, Costa Rica report, 1993 (Box 374)
      - Discovery, 1992 Dec. (Box 374)
      - Early Warning, 1992, 1993 (Box 374)
      - Eliminating World Poverty, 1997 (Box 374)
      - FLACSO [Faculdad Latinoamericana de Ciencias Sociales] booklets, 2007, 2 folders (Box 374)
      - Freidrich Ebert Stiftung booklets, 1988, 1991, undated (Box 374)
      - Garretón, Manuel Antonio articles, 1994-1997 (Box 374)
      - Global Future, 2002 (Box 374)
      - Hemisphere, 2006 (Box 374)
      - Henry L. Stimson Center Foreign Policy Project, 1996 (Box 374)
      - Honduran College of National Defense, Revista de Defensa Nacional (Box 374)
      - Human rights and economic justice, 1994 (Box 374)
      - Human Rights Watch, 1995 (Box 374)
      - Ideele, 2000 Feb.-2001 July, 1 of 4 folders (Box 374)
      - Ideele, 2000 Feb.-2001 July, 2-4 of 4 folders (Box 375)
      - Instituto Defensa Legal [IDL], 2000 (Box 375)
      - IRELA [Instituto de Relaciones Europeo-Latinamericanas], various papers, 1990-1995, 1-6 of 10 folders (Box 375)
      - IRELA [Instituto de Relaciones Europeo-Latinamericanas], various papers, 1990-1999, 7-10 of 10 folders (Box 376)
      - IDB reports, 2000, 2 folders (Box 376)
      - Interamerican Dialogue, 1992, 1994 (Box 376)
      - International Crisis Group, Latin American drug reports, 2008 (Box 376)
      - International Food Policy Research Institute, 1995 (Box 376)
      - Leadership Council for Inter-American Summitry, 1998-1999 (Box 376)
      - OAS [Organization of American States], 1994, 2007, undated, 2 folders (Box 376)
      - Perú military human rights program picture book, undated (Box 376)
      - Strategic Studies Institute, Mexico reports, 1994-1995 (Box 376)
      - United Methodist survey, 1995 (Box 377)
      - United Nations, various reports, 1988-1999, 8 folders (Box 377)
      - UNISA [University of South Africa] Latin American Report, 1993 (Box 377)
      - USAID, 1994, 2 folders (Box 377)
      - U.S. Army War College, Haiti Strategy, 1994 (Box 377)
      - WOLA, Rights and Development, various publications, 1988, 1998, 2003-2005, undated, 2 folders (Box 377)
      - Woodrow Wilson Center, Environmental Change and Security reports, 1998-1999, 2 folders (Box 377)
      - World Bank-related publications, 1994-1996, 1 of 3 folders (Box 377)
      - World Bank-related publications, 1994-1996, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 378)
    - Trade, 1992-2004, undated (Box 378-383)
      Files and correspondence on international trade, most involving the United States. The bulk of material relates to the passage and modification of the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) and the "fast track legislation" proposal put forth by President Clinton. Additional files relate to the Central American Free Trade Agreement (CAFTA), a proposed bilateral free trade agreement with Chile, the Mercado Común del Sur (MERCOSUR) regional trade agreement in South America, and a free trade agreement between Mexico and the European Union. Information on the World Trade Organization (WTO) may be found in a few files but is not a major focus.
    - U.S. Foreign Aid, 1995-2000, undated (Box 383-386)
      Material specifically relate to international aid from the United States. In addition to general subject files on U.S. appropriations for foreign aid, the bulk of the files concern the activities and funding for the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) and other sources of non-military foreign assistance.
    - World Bank, 1995-1999, undated (Box 386-390)
      Files, reports, and correspondence pertaining to the World Bank (WB), particularly its International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD) arm. These include memoranda by WB staff; performance evaluations of WB projects from within and outside the organization; sustainable development; the role of NGOs in WB policy; and reform efforts by James Wolfensohn, WB president from 1995-2005. In addition, copies of World Bank News may be found here.
  - Security Files, 1985-2005 and undated, 16 boxes
    Files primarily relating to Latin American security issues and U.S. involvement in them. Divided into the following folder groups: Police Reform; School of the Americas; Security Policy and Peacekeeping; U.S. Military; and WOLA Files. Police Reform files include country-specific folders for most of the countries in the Geographic Series, arranged in alphabetical order, regarding the conduct of civil authorities and associated human rights issues. A folder on police in Canada is also included. This section includes issues of Direitos Humanos, a Brazilian human rights publication in Portuguese; Dialogo Centroamericano, a Spanish-language publication on regional security and demilitarization; and a legislative document from Venezuela's Camera de Deputados regarding Venezuelan federal police. School of the Americas folders encompass courses, enrollment, press, and domestic legislative debate concerning the US Army School of the Americas (USARSA,SOA) located in Fort Benning, Georgia. A large portion includes academic as well as legislative material regarding human rights training at the SOA. The SOA files also include two declassified intelligence manuals on asset acquisition and interrogation. Security Policy and Peacekeeping includes information on military expenditure and folders concerning Latin American militaries, namely Venezuela, Chile, Argentina, Mexico, and one file on Ecuador and Perú. A number of printed publications and materials concerning the transition to new security strategies and policies is also included. This section also has a significant subsection of both United Nations files and files on arms trades, transfers, and terrorism. U.S. Military files concern American military policy toward Latin America and specifically concern physical placement of troops, economic aid, and educational training. The files include U.S. military budgets between 1989 and 1993 and significant subsections on civic action as well as military human rights training. WOLA Files are documents internal to WOLA regarding security-based initiatives and conferences. Specifically, information regarding the 1994 WOLA conference on police reform in Central America and Haiti is included. This grouping also includes the WOLA Manual for Civil Society as well as drafts and proofs for Citizen Security Monitor and other WOLA publications.
    - Police Reform, 1991-1999, undated (Box 391-394)
    - School of the Americas, 1985-1999, undated (Box 394-398)
    - Security Policy and Peacekeeping, 1989-2005, undated (Box 398-403)
    - U.S. Military, 1989-2002, undated (Box 403-406)
    - WOLA Files, 1992-2003, undated (Box 406-408)
- Sound Recordings Series, 1988-2005 and undated, 9 boxes
  Audio cassettes and one compact disc. Organized to mirror the structure in the main collection of the Geographic and Initiatives and Activities Series. Most are recordings of conferences and programs organized by WOLA. The recordings are arranged first by country in alphabetical order, after which follow a series of groupings related to specific conferences, or to topics such as Hurricane Mitch, drug policy, rights and development, and security. Approximately two boxes of cassettes at the end of the series are unidentified and unsorted.
  [Original recordings are closed to use. Technical Services staff may need to arrange to have listening copies made. Please contact Research Services before coming to use these materials.]
  - Argentina, 1996 (Box 409)
  - Bolivia, 2001-2002 (Box 409)
  - Brazil, 1989 (Box 409)
  - Chile, 1988 (Box 409)
  - Colombia, 1995-2005 (Box 409)
  - Colombia, 1995-2005 (Box 410)
  - Cuba, 1994-1999 (Box 410)
  - Ecuador, 1995 (Box 410)
  - El Salvador, 1989-1998 (Box 410)
  - Guatemala, 1990-2000 (Box 410)
  - Guatemala, 1990-2000 (Box 411)
  - Haiti, 1993-1996 (Box 411)
  - Honduras, 1988-1996 (Box 411)
  - Mexico, 1994-2002 (Box 411)
  - Mexico, 1994-2002 (Box 412)
  - Nicaragua, 1988-2000 (Box 412)
  - Panama, 1995-1998 (Box 412)
  - Perú, 1990-2002 (Box 412)
  - Perú, 1990-2002 (Box 413)
  - Venezuela, 1995-2005 (Box 413)
  - Conferences and Programs, 1988-2005 (Box 413)
  - Conferences and Programs, 1988-2005 (Box 414)
  - Drug Policy, 1994-2002 (Box 414)
  - Hurricane Mitch, 1999-2002 (Box 414)
  - Rights and Development, 1995-1998 (Box 414)
  - Security, 2001-2003 (Box 414)
  - Security, 2001-2003 (Box 415)
  - Unidentified recordings, 1988-2005, undated (Box 415)
  - Unidentified recordings, 1988-2005, undated (Box 416)
- Oversize Material, 1971-2000 and undated, 7 boxes
  Comprises large items from other series. The bulk of oversize material consists of newspapers and newspaper sections. Additional items include large serial publications, political posters, and broadsides. The majority of the material comes from the Patrick Ahern Files, part of the Chile Subseries and includes copies of the Santiago-based El Mercurio as well as the serials Solidaridad, and VEA. Politically-themed posters from Chile, Cuba, and Panama are also included.
  [Some papers are fragile. Technical services staff may need to make use copies prior to researcher use. Please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use these materials.]
  - Geographic Series
    - Argentina
      - Madres de Plaza de Mayo, 1986 (Box 417)